Guide to the Beverly Lowry Papers
The Wittliff Collections
Beverly Lowry Papers
1950-1998
The Wittliff Collections
Lowry, Beverly
SWWC.061
20 boxes Plus artifacts.
10 Linear Feet
Typescript drafts, correspondence, notes, clippings, journals, and photographs document the writing career of Beverly Lowry. The bulk of the papers relate to four of Lowry's seven published books, with The Perfect Sonya and Crossed Over being the most fully represented. The collection is arranged into the following seven series: Works, Correspondence, Clippings, Publicity, Computer disks, Personal, and Artifacts.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Information not available.
Related Materials
Beverly Lowry Additions (UPWC 04109)
Scope and Contents
Numerous typescript drafts, correspondence, notes, clippings, journals and photographs, ranging in date from 1950-1998, document Beverly Lowry's writing career. The bulk of the papers relate to four of Lowry's seven published books, with The Perfect Sonya and Crossed Over being the most fully represented.
Biographical Notes
Beverly Lowry was born August 10, 1938, in Memphis, Tennessee, and moved with her family at age six to Greenville, Mississippi. She attended the University of Mississippi (1956-58) and graduated with a B.A. from Memphis State University in 1960. She married Glenn Lowry in June 1960, and moved with him to Manhattan. There, she pursued acting and experimented in writing. After relocating to Houston in 1965, Lowry began to write stories, some of which became novels. Lowry began teaching fiction writing as an associate professor at the University of Houston in 1976, while also pursuing acting, and serving on boards for the Cultural Arts Council of Houston, and for Houston Festival. Her fiction writing has typically been set in Texas and Mississippi. Her first two novels, Come Back, Lolly Ray and Emma Blue were both set in Eunola, Mississippi a fictional town much like her hometown of Greenville. Her next three novels and one work of non-fiction were set in Texas, with her most recent novel, The Track of Real Desires, being again set in the fictional Eunola, Mississippi.
The Lowrys lived just outside San Marcos along the San Marcos River from 1981-1991. One of the Lowrys' two sons, Peter, died in a hit-and-run accident on the highway from San Marcos to their home in 1984. This experience and other personal losses in the early 1980s "caused a marked change in the tone of Lowry's fiction. Gone is her unqualified faith in the future; present is a new preoccupation with fate or chance, even a hint that felicity may invite disaster," (Contemporary Southern Writers, St. James Press, 1999). These themes of isolation and alienation appear in The Perfect Sonya(1987), The Track of Real Desires (1994), and clearly in Crossed Over: A Murder, A Memoir (1992). Beginning in 1989, Lowry approached and visited convicted pickaxe murderer Karla Faye Tucker, on death row in Hunstville, Texas. Crossed Over relates the story of Karla Faye Tucker as well as some of Lowry's own personal story, resulting in "far more than the usual true-crime tale. Lowry interwove the story of her own troubled son with a chilling account of Tucker's dangerously out-of-control life to achieve an understanding of the human being behind an ostensibly inhuman act; her leap of imagination and empathy enabled her, at last, to make peace with Peter's death," (Texas Monthly, Feb. 2001). Lowry moved to Los Angeles in the early 1990s, and currently teaches at George Mason University, in Virginia. She continues to write essays and non-fiction, and has been working on a biography of Madame C. J. Walker, the first Black woman to become a self-made millionaire.
Women authors, American; True crime stories; Fiction; Lowry, Beverly
- Works, 1950-1998
  Series Description
  The series is organized in the following subseries:
  Novels (1978-1998) Annotated typescripts for Daddy's Girl, The Perfect Sonya, Crossed Over, and The Track of Real Desires comprise the bulk of this subseries, with extensive research notes, correspondence, and photographs related to Crossed Over. Correspondence includes letters from Lowry to Karla Faye Tucker, 1989-1992, 1998, plus scattered letters from Jackie Oncken, John Adams of Great Britain, Ronald Kuntz of Ohio, and Dee Dee of Dallas.
  Poetry (undated) Works in this subseries are undated, although they appear to date from early on in Lowry's career. Poems have been arranged in alphabetical order by title; most are handwritten or typed.
  Short Stories (undated) Lowry's short stories have been arranged in alphabetical order. Although they are undated, it is probable that some date from as early as the late 1970s, when Lowry began writing short stories, some of which became novels. One story at the end of this subseries is by Glenn Lowry.
  Articles / Reviews by Lowry (1979-1998) This subseries includes a sampling of Lowry's published articles and reviews of books by others. Apart from one annotated galley, the remaining six articles and reviews are strictly photocopies of the published item.
  Research papers and school notes (1956-1959, undated) These research papers and school notes are from Lowry's drama and music coursework at the University of Mississippi and at Memphis State University, and are arranged in alphabetical order.
  Sketches (undated) One folder of pencil sketches of flowers, human figures, and other subjects, undated and unsigned, but likely by Lowry.
  - Novels, 1978-1998
    - Daddy's Girl, circa 1978-1980
      - Typescript, circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
      - Typescript, circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
    - The Perfect Sonya, 1977-1986, undated
      - "Pauline" - ATS, very early, many handwritten pages re: characters and plot, with sketches (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
      - "Pauline" - Early ATS, assorted pages (Box 2, Folder 4-6)
      - "Pauline", 1977 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - "Pauline" "Scraps" (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - "A Secret Attachment" synopsis, pages 1-11 and asst. (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - "A Fragile Balance" ATS (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Untitled - ATS, "stack 2-B," pages 1-321 (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
      - Untitled - ATS, "stack 3-A" (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Untitled - ATS, "stack 3-C" (Box 4, Folder 2-4)
      - Untitled - Assorted pages, through page 195 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Untitled - Assorted pages, 1-65 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Untitled - Assorted pages, 41-68 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Untitled - Assorted pages, 149-251 and others (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Untitled - Assorted pages, 47-168 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Untitled - Assorted pages, 47-341 and 26-81 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Untitled - Assorted pages, 52-183 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Untitled - Pages 1-224, photocopy (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Untitled - Assorted pages (Box 6, Folder 1-5)
      - "Footwork," typescript (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - "The Bear," typescript (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
      - "Snake Creek," typescript (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - "The Perfect Sonya" - Typescript, pages 1-222 and 77-125 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - "The Perfect Sonya" - Typescript, pages 1-307 (Box 7, Folder 5-6)
      - "The Perfect Sonya" - Typescript, pages 1-77 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - "The Perfect Sonya" - Typescript "Copy sent to NY, 11/1985", November 1985 (Box 8, Folder 2-3)
      - "The Perfect Sonya" - Typescript, "1/1986 #1", January 1986 (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
      - "The Perfect Sonya" - Typescript, "1/1986", January 1986 (Box 8, Folder 6-7)
      - "The Perfect Sonya" - Typescript, "2/1986", February 1986 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
      - "The Perfect Sonya" - Typescript, fragment, "1/1986 and 6/1986", January and June 1986 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - "The Perfect Sonya" - Typescript, "6/25/86", June 25, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - "The Perfect Sonya" - Typescript, "#2" (Box 9, Folder 5-7)
      - "The Perfect Sonya" - Typescript, pages 1-334 (Box 9, Folder 8-9)
      - "The Perfect Sonya" - Typescript, with copy editing (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
      - "The Perfect Sonya" - Galley (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Crossed Over: A Murder, A Memoir, 1989-1998, undated
      - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence, January-March 1990 (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence, April-July 1990 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence, August-December 1990 (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 3-4)
      - Correspondence, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 6)
      - Correspondence, undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - Notes - includes photos of interview with Lowry outside the Texas Prison Museum and prison in Huntsville, TX, 1997, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
      - Clippings, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 9)
      - Clippings, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 10-11)
      - Clippings, January 1998 (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
      - Clippings, February 1-4, 1998 (Box 12, Folder 3-4)
      - Clippings, February 5-10, 1998 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
      - Clippings, February 11-28, 1998 (Box 13, Folder 3-4)
      - Clippings, March-April, 1998 (Box 13, Folder 5-6)
      - Clippings, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Clippings - German language articles (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Clippings - New Kids on the Block (collected by Karla Faye Tucker) (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - Criminal Justice System documents - petition for 30 day reprieve from execution (also includes e-mail correspondence and articles printed from web regarding Tucker's execution), 1997-1998 (Box 13, Folder 10-11)
      - Texas Department of Criminal Justice public info file on Karla Faye Tucker (Box 13, Folder 12)
      - Typescript, December 1989 (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - Typescript, May 1990 (Box 14, Folder 2-3)
      - Typescript, June 1990 (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - Typescript, October 1990 (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - Typescript, November 1990 (Box 15, Folder 1-3)
      - Typescript, undated (Box 15, Folder 4-5, Box 16, Folder 1-2)
      - Clean typescript (Box 16, Folder 3-4)
      - Publicity - two black and white 5x7 publicity stills, one Knopf booklet of excerpts (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - New Yorker article - Typescripts and editorial correspondence (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - New Yorker article - Annotated galleys (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - Interviews - Diane Rehm Show, WAMU radio (January 1998) and "DAR" (January 9, 1998) (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Interview - Fox in Depth, January 12, 1998 (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - Interviews with Today Show, CNN, and Charles Grodin CNBC, February 2-3, 1998 (Box 17, Folder 3)
      - Interviews with Brian Williams MSNBC and CNN Talkback Live, February 2-3, 1998 (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - Interview with Newsnight, BBC, undated (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - The Track of Real Desires, 1989, undated
      - Typescripts - partial, annotated drafts - working title "Those Two", August 21, 1989 (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - Typescripts - partial, annotated drafts, August 25, 1989 (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - Typescripts - partial, annotated drafts, September 8, 1989 (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - Typescripts - partial, annotated drafts, September 11, 1989 (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - Typescripts - partial, annotated drafts, undated (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Poetry, undated
    - Go Down Death (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - I Love You (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - IOU (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Murder She Says (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Short Stories, undated
    - What Love Can Do (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - The Almost Perfect Day (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - And Nice Girls Don't Finish at All (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - A Half Moon is a Broken Moon (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - Home for Christmas (Box 18, Folder 14)
    - If It's Not One Thing, It's Another (Box 18, Folder 15)
    - Letha-or-Sometimes Knowing Knows Nothing (Box 18, Folder 16)
    - [Lila Lee Shannon Story] (Box 18, Folder 17)
    - [Lily story fragments] (Box 18, Folder 18)
    - Luckiest Person I Know (Box 18, Folder 19)
    - Mother's Day (Box 18, Folder 20)
    - Old Love on a Cold Night (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - One of Life's Small Necessities (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - The Pail Lady (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Some Time to Myself (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Thomas (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Unanswered Prayer (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Virgin (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Untitled (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Notes and fragments (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - It's Just a GAME by Glenn Lowry (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Articles / Reviews by Lowry, 1979-1998
    - "Born to Preen: Why Southern Girls Dominate Beauty Contests" (photocopy of published article), September 1997 (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - The Creoletown Crux (photocopy of published review), 1980 (Box 19, Folder 12)
    - "Grilled Portobellos and William Faulkner," New York Times, April 1998 (Box 19, Folder 13)
    - The Habit of Being: Letters of Flannery O'Connor, edited by Sally Fitzgerald, review by Lowry, annotated galley, 1979 (Box 19, Folder 14)
    - "Puberty" Southern Magazine (photocopy of published article), undated (Box 19, Folder 15)
    - "Separated at Birth?" (film review) American Way (photocopy of published article), undated (Box 19, Folder 16)
    - "Southern Daddies, Southern Girls" Southern Magazine (photocopy of published article), February 1987 (Box 19, Folder 17)
  - Research papers and school notes, 1956-1959, undated
    - British theater paper, undated (Box 19, Folder 18)
    - English drama class notes, undated (Box 19, Folder 19)
    - An Examination of Barabas, December 1959 (Box 19, Folder 20)
    - I Speak for Democracy (Box 19, Folder 21)
    - King Lear - an analysis paper (Box 19, Folder 22)
    - Mourning Become Electra (Box 19, Folder 23)
    - Music 423 class notes (Box 19, Folder 24)
    - Original Oratory (Box 19, Folder 25)
    - The Paths of Glory (Box 19, Folder 26)
    - Play fragment, untitled (Box 19, Folder 27)
    - Religion (Box 19, Folder 28)
    - Success in Securing Desirable Employment, December 1956 (Box 19, Folder 29)
    - We Seek the Higher Things (Box 19, Folder 30)
  - Sketches, undated
    - Sketches (Box 19, Folder 31)
- Correspondence, 1978-1990, undated
  This series is comprised of one folder of correspondence including personal notes and publishers' requests of Lowry to read specific books and comment on them.
  - 1978-1990, undated (Box 20, Folder 1)
- Clippings, 1977-1982, undated
  Newsclippings in this series relate to Lowry's writing career, and have been arranged chronologically.
  - 1977-1982 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - undated (Box 20, Folder 3)
- Publicity, undated
  Four undated photographs are included in this series: 3 black and white photographs of a Come Back, Lolly Ray manuscript exhibit, and 1 color photograph of Lowry at a book signing for the short story compilation, Common Bonds, with other authors
  - Three black and white photographs of Come Back, Lolly Ray manuscript exhibit (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - One color photograph of Lowry at book signing for Common Bonds, with other authors (Box 20, Folder 5)
- Computer disks, undated (Box 20, Folder 6-7)
  Fourteen 5.5" floppy disks, many labeled as "Pauline," which was a working title for The Perfect Sonya.
- Personal, 1960-1975, undated
  This series includes journals, a college diploma, and materials related to Lowry's sons. The three bound journals are undated, and include notes about Lowry's daily life and writing projects. The college diploma is from Memphis State University, 1960, and includes a torn photograph of Lowry from that time period. The materials related to Lowry's sons include poetry and drawings to and by Peter and Colin Lowry.
  - Journals, undated (Box 20, Folder 8-10)
  - Diploma. Memphis State University, 1960 (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - Children - poetry, drawings to and by Peter and Colin Lowry, 1966-1975 (Box 20, Folder 12)
- Artifacts, undated
  This series contains one item: a Kaypro word processor.
  - Kaypro word processor